Guide to the Bureau of Applied Social Research records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series I: Project Index
  - Lazarsfeld, G. Nash, & P. Nash The College Financial Aid Officer, 1966-1967, (B-1041-1: 41 pp., B-1041-2: 54 pp., B-1041-3: 39 pp., B-1041-4: 367 pp., B-1041-5: 127 pp.: 20 folders containing Project Memo, Paper, Library Log, Proposal, Project Memo #2, Preliminary Reports, Interviews with answers, Bound Reports, Article, Bound Report, Codebook, Questionnaires, Memo & Misc., Periodical, Article, Codebook, Questionnaires & Codebook, Codebook & Marginals, Questionnaire and one empty folder cross-referenced to record A-548. that apparently contained Report/Paper entitled the "Current Status of Financial Aid Administration." ) (Box 84, Folder B-1041)
    [B-1041-1 A Review of the Literature on College Administrators and Admissions. B-1041-2 History of the Questionnaire for Directors of Financial Aid. B-1041-3 Student Financial Aid-College and University-a Review of the Literature and Research. B-1041-4 This report describes the aid director's work, his sources of satisfaction and dissatisfaction, how financial aid is organized at the college level and the relationship between the organization of aid administration and the effectiveness of the aid program. B-1041-5 Based on questionnaires returned by directors of undergraduate financial aid at 849 universities and colleges, as well as data obtained from American Universities and Colleges, this report analyzes financial aid policies of four-year colleges and universities in the U.S. It also describes how a limited number of institutional characteristics relate to one another and how they vary from one type of institution to another. Reports: B-1041-1 through B-1041-5 Articles: G. Nash 1968 (1, 3), 1969 (1, 3) Dissertation: G. Nash 1969]
  - Steven F. Cohn Problems in the Breakdown of Democracy, 1950's (?) -1969, (3 folders containing Dissertation Summary, Library Log, Questionnaire & Codebook) (Box 84, Folder S-1041)
  - Glaser Crossnational Comparison of Factory Organization, 1967, ( 40 Folders and One Book. Book- Bound Final Study. Folders contain Codebooks, Notes (Spanish), Papers (Italian), Articles, Periodical (German), Book, Meeting Minutes, Appendix, Proposal, Report Draft, Papers (French), Proposal Supplement, Paper Draft, Memo Draft, Study Draft (Says "Proposal"), Paper, Outline, Article, Paper (Background Memo), Plans, Hypothesis, Comparative Paper, Short Paper, Meeting Minutes, Project Summary & Correspondence, Comparative Study, Papers (French), Project Bibliography (French), Papers (French), Proposal (French), Misc., Proposal, Draft Proposal, Final Report, Interview (French), Periodical, Project Results Report. ) (Box 85, Folder B-1042)
    [Articles: Schmidt 1969, Glaser 1970, 1975 (1) Foreign Publications: Gallino 1969, Altmann 1971]
  - Kenneth Lenihan Performance of Vista Volunteers in the Field, 1966, (275 pp.: 13 folders containing Interview Results, Questionnaires, Interview Schedule, Dissertation Report, Proposal, Research Overview, Research Topics, Misc., VISTA Report Location Abstract, Case study reports, Field Notes & Reports and one empty folder that apparently contained Control Report by Lenihan of which a copy is supposed to be in Vienna.) (Box 85 & 86, Folder B-1043)
    [Vista's purpose is to provide social agencies with full-time Volunteers to help combat poverty in local neighborhoods. This report discusses their training, job performance and experiences, and makes recommendations for changes so that their contribution would be more valuable. Methodological appendix, questionnaire, and interview schedules are included. Report: B-1043 Dissertation: Lenihan 1974]
  - Kenneth Lenihan (?) Performance of Vista Volunteers in the Field (?), 1966, (Four seperately bound Codebooks ) (Box 86, Folder S-1043)
  - Kadushin & Ritterband The Nonreturn of Israeli Students, 1966-1978, (10 folders containing BASR articles, cross-referenced to record A-459, Questionnaire results, Questionnaire in English, Questionnaire in Hebrew, Proposal, Hebrew papers, Memo, Marginals, BASR Bound Final Report ) (Box 86, Folder B-1044)
    [Report: B-1044 Book: Ritterband 1977 Articles: Ritterband 1966, 1969, 1970 Dissertation: Ritterband 1968]
  - Wallace Study of Interpersonal Violence, 1965, (3 Folders containing Proposal, Paper, Misc. Report: not available) (Box 86, Folder B-1045)
  - Jaffe & Adams Continuing Research on Higher Education in the United States (American Higher Education in Transition), 1969-1972, (B-1046-1: 239 pp., B-1046-2: 129 pp., B-1046-3: 120 pp., B-1046-4: 133 pp.:8 folder Folders contain Articles, Proposal, Paper, Periodical Photocopy, Progress Reports, Progress Report & Findings, Misc. materials and one empty folder that apparently contained study by Adams & Jaffe, entitled "American Higher Education in Transition,"a copy of whose contents are supposed to be in Vienna. ) (Box 86, Folder B-1046)
    [B-1046-1 This specifies the interlocking student and institutional variables which influence college attendance. Newer variables are distinguished from the more traditional ones and rough assessments of the relative significance of each type for the near future are made. B-1046-2 Technical Progress Report: Follow-up of Cross-Section of 1965-1966 High School Seniors. B-1046-3 Technical Progress Report: Follow-up of Cross-Section of 1965-1966 High School Seniors. B-1046-4 These (B-1046-2,3,4) cover the progress of the project and the major findings for the longitudinal follow-up of the 1965-1966 Current Population Survey of high school seniors. Report: B-1046-1 through B-1046-4 Articles: Adams 1968, 1969 (1, 2), 1970, Jaffe & Adams 1970, Froomkin 1970, Adams & Jaffe 1971, Jaffe & Adams 1971, Adams 1972, Jaffe & Adams 1972 (1, 2), Adams 1974]
  - Makler Portuguese Business Elites, 1963, (9 Folders and 4 Books Books (4 in Spanish, Codebooks?). Folders contain Misc., Questionnaire Results Form, Book (Spanish), Proposal, Library Log, Paper, Bound Comparative Studies, Codebooks (Spanish), BASR Bound Final Report (2 volumes) and one empty folder with a note recording the locations of Articles that it apparently contained.) (Box 86 & 87, Folder S-1046)
    [Book: Makler 1969 Articles: Makler 1967, 1974 Dissertation: Makler 1968]
  - David Caplovitz Demonstration study for Low-Income Housing, 1965, (2 folders containing Proposal & grants collected, Project Summary) (Box 87, Folder B-1047)
  - E. S. Wellhofer Correlates of Political Participation in Mexico, 1966, (1 folder and one book. Paper for Juan Linz) (Box 87, Folder S-1047)
  - Carol H. Weiss Problems of Data Collection from Low-Income Populations (Low Income Interviewing), 1966, (84 pp.: 7 folders containing Paper, Bibliographies, Proposal, Project Summary, BASR Bound Final Report) (Box 87, Folder B-1048)
    [See also B-1121.
    The basic concern of this report was with identifying the sources of error in interview responses. A review of the literature was carried out and a classified and annotated bibliography resulted. The most relevant of the literature was then analyzed to derive some insights into the nature and extent of the interviewing problem with low-income people. Report: B-1048 Article: Weiss 1966]
  - Etzioni Extrapolation of 1045 Social Science Findings to International Analysis, 1967, (199 pp.: 3 folders containing Grant Application, Misc., Articles and one empty folder that apparently contained Final Report entitled "Sociological Findings & Security Systems in the Classroom,"of which a copy is supposed to be in Vienna.) (Box 87, Folder B-1049)
    [This report investigates non-conventional uses of sociology: the application of sociology in the analysis of interaction between nations and the conditions for cooperation or avoidance of extreme conflict; and the logical nature of emergent properties of macroscopic systems and the case for focusing more efforts in future research on that level. Report: B-1049 Articles: Etzioni 1967, 1969]
  - George and Patricia Nash Characteristics of the Colleges of Peace Corps Applicants, 1966, (90 pp.: 2 Books and 4 folders Books- BASR Bound Statistical Appendices. Folders contain Proposal, Library Log, Summary of Study, Misc. and two empty folders that apparently respectively contained the Nash Report marked Confidential and entitled "From Which College Came the Peace Corps Volunteers," and an attached Appendix of which copies of both are supposed to be in Vienna, while the second empty folder apparently contained a copy of the above Appendix. .) (Box 87, Folder B-1050)
    [This report analyzes characteristics of colleges and the relationship of these characteristics to the number of applications to the Peace Corps from these colleges. The recruiting efforts of the Peace Corps are also analyzed. Report: B-1050]
  - Amitai Etzioni and Nina Toren Application of the Theory of Compliance to Social Work Administration, 1969, (320 pp.: 2 folders containing Project Summary, BASR Bound Report and one empty folder.which apparently contained copy of Paper by Etzioni entitled 'The Semi-Professions and their Organization.") (Box 87, Folder B-1052)
    [This analysis of the structure and practice of social work discusses the formally established aims of social work and the means by which they can be achieved more effectively. The elucidation of the significance of the semi-professional attributes and their effects on social work practice are the main themes of this study. Report: B-1052 Book: Etzioni 1969 Article: Etzioni 1966 Dissertation: Toren 1969]
  - Jeanne Hazen Comparison of Social Democratic& Communist parties in Sacndinavian Democracies, 1966, (1 folder containing Proposal) (Box 87, Folder S-1052)
  - George and Patricia Nash Attitudes During the Blackout, 1965, (18 pp.: 6 folders containing 107 Cards, Interview Codebook, Preliminary Draft of Report, Periodical, Misc., Interview) (Box 87, Folder B-1053)
    [This report discusses what the attitudes of people were during the blackout of November 9, 1965. 103 people were interviewed to determine what they thought caused the blackout and what they expected to happen. Interview guide included. Report: B-1053]
  - Charles Kadushin Competition in the Classroom, 1966, (4 folders containing Library Log, Questionnaire, Misc., Questionnaire Appendix) (Box 88, Folder S-1053)
  - George Nash and Stephen Cole Drivers During the Transit Strike, 1966, (4 pp.: 1 folder containing Very Rough Paper Draft) (Box 88, Folder B-1054)
    [During the transit strike, 114 drivers were interviewed about their cooperation with the Mayor's appeal for drivers to bring in extra people. Cooperation is related to situational and personality variables. Report: B-1054]
  - Carol H. Weiss, et al. Toward Research on Community Action Agencies: Key Variables and Research Instruments (Guide to Organizational Data on Community Action Programs), 1966, (218 pp.: 3 folders containing Draft Proposal, Paper & Misc., BASR Bound Report) (Box 88, Folder B-1055)
    [This project developed an inventory of key variables which would describe and differentiate Community Action Agencies and which would be relevant to the effectiveness of CAA programs. This report consists of a comprehensive bibliography of organizational literature and interview guides for various people concerned with the CAA programs. A critical review of these materials is also included. Report: B-1055]
  - Sam Sieber and George Nash Activities Related to Urban & Minority problems at American Universities, 1968-1969, (2 folders containing Papers, Bound Reports-Cross referenced to A-585.) (Box 88, Folder J-1055)
  - Fred Sherrow, David Caplovitz and Paul Ritterband Volunteers to Israel (Jewish Peace Corps, Sherut La'am Program), 1968, (139 pp.: 3 folders containing Questionnaires, Proposal, Article photocopy and one empty folder with a copy of Report/Paper entitled "Jewish Peace Corps Comes to Israrel," of which a copy is supposed to be available in Vienna.) (Box 88, Folder B-1059)
    [This is a study of more than 100 American college students who volunteered for a year of service in Israel in a program entitled Sherut La'am. Questionnaires were administered to participants before and after a 2-week orientation session prior to departure and before return from the year in Israel. The volunteers' reactions to the administration and services of the program as well as their jobs in Israel are analyzed. Report: B-1059 Article: Sherrow & Ritterband 1970]
  - David Caplovitz Consumers in Trouble (Debtors in Default), 1968-1970, (15 folders containig Interviews & Misc., Questionnaires, BASR Bound Report (Vol. I), Project Summaries, Papers, Conference Paper, BASR Bound Report (Vol. II), Testimony Transcript, Proposal, Codesheet & intstructions, Preliminary Study, Paper, Survey Report, Periodical Report, and one empty folder which apparently contained Report/Study entitled "Consumers in Trouble;A Study of Debtors in Default," by Caplovitz of which a copy is supposed to be in Vienna. ) (Box 88, Folder B-1060)
    [Reports: B-1060-1; B-1060-2 Book: Caplovitz 1974 Article: Caplovitz 1968 Dissertations: Rubin 1971, Single 1973]
  - Susan E. Flusser Workshop on Value of Higher Education, 1967, (1 folder containing Questionnaire) (Box 88, Folder J-1060)
  - Sieber Educational Research Training Program, 1966-1967, (9 folders Proposal, Progress Report, Codebooks, Meeting Report, Miscellaneous, Seminar Paper, Misc. Materials, Codebooks) (Box 88, Folder B-1061)
  - Kameno Social Sources of College Drop-Out, 1965 (?), (1 folder containing Proposal) (Box 89, Folder S-1061)
  - Anna Lee Hopson Centers for Education in Democracy Evaluation, 1966, (186 pp.: 4 folders containing Questionnaires, Misc., Statistical Appendix and one empty folder which apparently contained Report/Article entitled "An Evaluation of the Contribution of the Centers for Education in Democracy," of which a copy of is supposed to be available in Vienna.) (Box 89, Folder B-1062)
    [This is a before and after study of the attitudes of 168 teenagers who attended a six-week summer camp either in Fieldston, New York, or in Barbourville, Kentucky. The independent variables of sex, economic background and race were related to friendship formation and attitude change toward civil rights and anti-poverty action. Comparisons were made between the conservative and liberal trainees. Questionnaire included. Report: B-1062]
  - Jaffe Economic and Demographic Factors Associated with Retirement of Men from the U.S. Labor Force, 1966, (6 folders containing Articles, Periodicals, Paper, Proposal, Photocopies, Misc.) (Box 89, Folder B-1063)
    [Report: not available Monograph: Jaffe 1972 Articles: Jaffe 1966 (1, 4), Jaffe 1967 (1, 2), Jaffe 1970 (2), 1971]
  - John J. Lally Study of Psychiatrists and Religion, 1967, (1 folder containing Codebook) (Box 89, Folder S-1063)
  - Bernard Levenson Employment Opportunities of Negro and White Youth, `1967-1973, (177 pp.: 6 folders containing Proposal, Statistical Material, Interim Reports, Early Reports, BASR Bound Report, Statistical Material etc...) (Box 89, Folder B-1064)
    [This study analyzes the inequalities which exist between comparably educated blacks and whites in Baltimore, in obtaining jobs, and in wages paid. Report: B-1064 Articles: Levenson & McDill 1966, Baker & Levenson 1975, 1976 Dissertation: Baker 1970]
  - Goode Family Structures and Mobility Processes, 1966, (1 Folder Project Summary) (Box 89, Folder B-1065)
    [See publications of B-1025.
  - Stevens H. Clarke and Julius Surkis Application of Electronic Computer Techniques to Racial Integration in School Systems, 1967, (50 pp.: 3 folders containing Library Log, Proposals (Second Copy of Propsal supposed to be in Vienna)) (Box 89, Folder B-1066)
    [This report describes in detail a computerized system for assigning students to schools to maximize racial integration while minimizing travel time and cost. Using the computer system, MINTRAN-MPS/ 360, a table of assignment of students to school buildings is drawn up which places each student in a school with a minimum of total daily student transportation time subject to certain constraints. Report: B-1066]
  - Caroline S. Hodges Measuring Educational Research Quality and Its Correlates, 1967, (2 folders containing Bound Paper, Misc.) (Box 89, Folder S-1066)
  - Schegloff Formal Analysis of Natural, Oral, Verbal Communicaton: Details of Police-Public Interaction under Normal and Disaster Conditions, 1967, (6 folders containing Radio Transcripts, Papers, Research Notes, Paper, Proposal, Transcripts) (Box 89, Folder B-1067)
    [Report: not available Article: Schegloff 1968 Dissertation: Schegloff 1967]
  - Seymour Warkov Professional and Technical Careers in the Middle years, 1966-1967, (2 folders containing Proposal, Misc) (Box 89, Folder B-1068)
  - George Nash and Julian H. Nixon The New York City Urban Corps, 1967, (264 pp.: 9 folders containing and 1 Book Book-Bound Final Report. Folders contain Proposals, Interview, Questionnaire, Questionnaires & Questionnaire results, Field Report, Memo, Paper, Miscellaneous materials, and one empty folder that apparently contained report/paper entitled "Response to Challenge: The New York City Urban Corps,"of which a copy is supposed to be in Vienna..) (Box 89, Folder B-1069)
    [600 student interns on summer jobs in 13 New York City agencies answered questionnaires on their experiences. Supervisors' reports and field observations were also used. The analysis compares experiences in different agencies and reported effects on students and the agencies. Report: B-1069]
  - H. Hyman The Extent and Consequences of Obsevability in the School System-Cross-Referenced with B-1011., 1966, (1 folder containing Proposal) (Box 89, Folder S-1069)
  - David E. Wilder The Potential Community Role of a College (Community Needs in the Danbury Area), 1966, (74 pp.: 2 folders containing Final Report, Proposal) (Box 89, Folder B-1070)
    [Interviewing 180 selected community leaders, this report discusses the problems of Danbury, Conn., such as poverty and race relations, planning and growth, leadership, government, and education. The existing facilities for meeting these problems are described. The image of Danbury State College in the eyes of the community is also discussed and recommendations are made for coping with these problems. Report: B-1070]
  - Validity of Interview Responses of Welfare Mothers (Weiss), 1967-1969, (7 Folders, Folders contain Periodical Reprint, Questionnaire, Project Summary, Papers, Articles, Miscell. and Project Description and one empty folder of that apparently contained the final Report entitled "Validity of Interview responses by Welfare Mothers," by Carol Weiss of which a copy is supposed to be available in Vienna. ) (Box 90, Folder B-1071)
    [Report: B-1071 1968]
  - A Study of Washington, D.C. Teachers (Wilder & Hopson), 1960's (?), (One Folder Miscell. and one empty folder of which apparently contained Paper/Report entitled "Study of Teachers in Public Schools in Washington, D.C.," and of which a copy is supposed to be in Vienna.) (Box 90, Folder B-1072)
    [Report: B-1072 1967; Dissertations: Goldberg 1969, Bodard 1970]
  - Closed File Narcotic Addiction Study (Caplow, Lazarsfeld, Nash), 1967-1971, (One Letter, 16 Bound Books, and 53 Folders. Letter-June 1977-about closure of file. Bound Books-!-Narcotics Addiction Study (Vol I) -notes and Volumes II-XIII, Volume XIV-notes, Volume XV-Addict Study and Volume XVI-College Drug Use. Folders- Correspondence, Periodical Rewprints, Project Histories, Memos, Miscell., Questionnaires, Coding, Paperss, Questionnaire Responses, Progress Report, Marginals, Paper, Bound Reports, Memo proposal, Periodical Photocopy, Anecdotal and Formal papers, Survey Tabulations, Bound Report (regarding Drug Study itself), Memos, Anecdotal papers, Qustionnaires, Anecdotal Papers, Interview Material, Paper, Paper on Heroin, Questionnaire(Phoenix House), Papers, Paper(regarding Questionnaire Responses), Community Study, paper, Coding Information,Questionnaires, Interview Guides, Questionnaires, Coding Material, Questionnaires, Coding Papers, Qustionnaires, Code Sheets, Methodological Notes, Notes, Paper Draft, Papers, Interview reponses, Papers, Interviews, Questionnaires and Marginals, Papers, Bound papewrs, Bound Survey Results, Case Reports and one emty folder.) (Box 90, 91 & 92, Folder B-1073)
    [Reports of this study were never officially released; copies may be consulted in the BASR project files, Herbert Lehman Social Science Library, Columbia University.]
  - Michae;l McKee Student Attitude Study, 1966, (One Folder Questionnaire) (Box 92, Folder S-1073)
  - Taxonomy of Higher Education (Sieber), 1966, (Six Folders, Folders Contain Proposal, Paper, Note available in A656), Progress report, Memos, Basr Bound Report and Paper. ) (Box 92, Folder B-1074)
    [Report: B-1074 1968; Article: Sieber 1971]
  - Robert Bernice Hill Merton's Role Types & Paradigm of Deviance, 1967, (Two Folders Folders contain Basr Bound report and proposal) (Box 92, Folder S-1074)
  - African Data Archive Project (Hopkins & Wallerstein), 1967, (Two Folders Periodical Article Reprint, Proposals and Abstract) (Box 92, Folder B- 1075)
    [Article: Hopkins & Wallerstein 1971]
  - The Social Composition of the Grand Jury (Dibble), 1967, (Two Folders Folders contain Basr Bound Reports and Summary) (Box 92, Folder B-1076)
    [Report: B-1076 1967]
  - Sam Sieber Analysis of U.S. Office of Education Training Programs (Sieber), 1967-1968, (Three Folders Folders contain Proposals, Summary, Codebooks and Study and one empty folder which contained a copy of study entitled "Analysis of U.S.O.F. Research Training Programs," & Questionnaire, copies of whose contents are supposed to be in Vienna..) (Box 92, Folder B- 1077)
    [Report: B-1077 1968]
  - Mervin Verbst Study of Student's Religious Attitudes, 1967, (One Folder Questionnaire) (Box 92, Folder S-1077)
  - Review of Federal Student Loan Programs (G. Nash & P. Nash), 1967, (Report: B-1078-1, B-1078-2 1967Twelve Folders, Folders Contain Questionnaires, Questionnaire Results, Congressional Reports, Report, Questionnaire Results, Basr Bound Reports, Bound Study, Bound Final Report and Periodical Article Reprints. ) (Box 92, Folder B- 1078)
    [Articles: G. Nash 1968 (2), 1969 (1)]
  - Lou Gold King's County Brooklyn 1966 Voter Study, 1966, (One Folder Questionnaire) (Box 92, Folder S-1078)
  - Communication of Social Science Information (Davison & Hopson), 1967-1968, (Two Folders Folders Contain Summary proposals and BASR Bound Report) (Box 92, Folder B-1079)
    [Report: B-1079 1968]
  - Ralph Bisco Council of Social Science Data Archives (Glaser); Monograph: Glaser 1967; Book: Bisco 1970, 1965-1970, (26 Folders, Folders Contain; BASR Bound Periodical; Miscellaneous Grant proposal; Periodical Reprint and Statements of Purpose; Final Report; Social Science Council Constitution; Memos; Paper; Booklit; Periodical Reprint; Paper Draft; Paper; Memos; Booklet and Archives; Periodical and Booklet; Paper; Council Miscellaneous; Membership Applications, etc., Miscellaneous Finance Matters, Reprinted legal Notes, Conference Notes, Conference Minutes, etc., Conference Schedule, Personnel Listings, Memos, Miscell. Bound Proposal and one empty folder which apparently contained book entitiled "Data Bases,Computers & the Social Sciences," by Ralph Bisco. ) (Box 93, Folder B-1080)
    [Articles: Glaser & Bisco 1966, Bisco 1967, Nixon 1967, Glaser 1969]
  - Anonymous Interview for Chief of Medical Service, 1960's (?), (One Folder Questionnaire) (Box 93, Folder S-1080)
  - Macrosociology (Etzioni); [Book], Etzioni, 1968, (2 folders) (Box 93, Folder B-1081)
    [Articles: Etzioni & Lehman 1967, Etzioni 1967, 1970.